## Michael Lee

Data Visualization Developer

### SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

4+ years applying open source libraries to analyze data and build products that drive knowledge acquisition and decision making. Whether working independently or collaboratively I'm able to contribute meaningful work through strong communication skills, critically evaluating challenging data problems, and the attention to diverse audiences across my professional career.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### **RESEARCH ASSOCIATE**

<u>American Institutes for Research</u> (July 2015 - Present)

- Co-authored the <u>EdSurvey</u> R package for analysis of survey data using NCES statistical methods, including the development of R functions from scratch (accompanied by acceptance tests), two vignettes, and presentation of the package's practical use for researchers at 2016 and 2017 AERA workshops
- Co-authored the **NAEPprimer** data package
- Collaborated with designers to automate the production of summary reports, each featuring a custom-designed LaTeX template embedded with unique ggplot2 visualizations illustrating data trends
- Wrote R scripts to review data sets in longitudinal surveys to meet compliance standards
- Developed over 10 unique animations for social media distribution at twitter.com/EdNCES

### FREELANCE/INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR

The Ballengee Group (November 2014 - February 2015)

- Created a database of baseball performance and salary data exclusively using R software
- Modeled salary expectations for over 80 major and minor league baseball players across a 10 year period using machine learning methods

www.mikelee.co (November 2014 - Present)

• Online portfolio of data visualizations and independent analyses; implemented with Bulma and hosted on GitHub

### SPECIAL EDUCATION TEACHER

Milwaukee Public Schools (Aug 2011 - June 2013)

- Utilized performance data to develop lesson plans, activities, and interventions appropriate for students with diverse learning needs and disabilities
- Collaborated with staff to create Individualized Education Programs for students with significant behavioral challenges
- Moderated behavior charts and implemented effective classroom management techniques

### **EDUCATION**

# MASTERS OF ARTS, URBAN EDUCATION

2013 Cardin

Cardinal Stritch University, Milwaukee, WI

Washington, DC Phone: 414-550-3410

Email: mdlee12@amail.com

## BACHELOR OF SCIENCE, PSYCHOLOGY

2011

University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI

## **SPECIALTIES**

Data Analysis & Processing
Data Visualization
Web Development
Web Scraping
R Package Development
Technical Writing
Workshop Moderation

#### SKILLS

#### **Data Toolbox**

R // Python // SQL // Shiny // Excel

### Web Development

HTML5 // D3.js // CSS // Bootstrap // Git // Jekyll // Hugo

## **Teaching**

Lesson Planning //
Workshops //
Differentiated Instruction